VINCENT YAP

9455 3556

<u>vyap2000@gmail.com</u> www.linkedin.com/in/vincentyap

CAREER PROFILE

An experienced Data Analytics, Data Scientist with expertise in data analytics, big data and data science and business intelligence within Telco, Finance & Banking, Education, Government, and IT software industries within Australia and Singapore. Most recently working as the Data Analytics Manager & Architect for Learning Lab in Singapore. Skills in predictive analytic modelling, BI consulting, data analysis, management, leadership, and support capabilities.

Part of a senior management team contributing to several initiatives and projects through to their full development life cycle to achieve significant business goals including cost-effective infrastructure in-sourcing, reduced IT spending, best practices & data governance with creation of competitive business advantages.

KEY CAPABILITIES

- Data Science Predictive Data Modelling, Supervised & Unsupervised Machine Learning, Regression & Classification, Natural Language Processing (NLP), Neural Network, Deep Learning, Azure / AWS Cloud Computing - Machine Learning.
- **Big Data** Hadoop DataLake, YARN, HDFS/HBase, AWS EMR, Elastic Search, Kafka, Scala, Hive, MapReduce, Pig, Oozie, Spark 2, ML, Data Pipelines
- Business Intelligence Over 15 years of BI experience with various application tools and Data Mart, Data Lake, Data warehousing, Reporting Analytics, KPI Dashboard, ETL, data transformation and data governance, best practices.
- **Project Management** Responsible for organizing, planning, motivating, mentoring and controlling resources, procedures and best practices. E.g. SAFE (Scaled Lean Agile)
- **Consultancy** Provided BO solution for business' requirement.
- **Support & Services** Provided technical support / service delivery for BI and non BI related incidents / issues
- **Design and Development** Provided analysis, requirement specification, designing, testing, deploying, upgrading, migrating and implementation of BI / BO solution.
- Stakeholders & Vendor Management Managed communication, milestones, and deliverables with various stakeholders and business owners. Managed internal and external vendors and supplier relations.
- Business Continuity Responsible for business continuity plan (BCP) for servers, Datawarehousing, datacentre management, network protocols, multiple servers' clusters/forestintegration.
- Change & Release Management Provided BI solution presentation & training to different levels of org users from board of directors, stakeholders and end users.

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Data Science	Python for Data Science, Supervised and Unsupervised Machine Learning, Recommender system, Natural Language Processing, Deep Learning, Neural Network, Big Data Analysis. AWS Cloud Machine Learning
Big Data	Data Lake, Hadoop YARN, HDFS, Cloudera, AWS EMR, Elastic Search, Kafka, Sqoop, Spark2, Scala, Hive, HBase, Map Reduce, HANA, Oozie

BI Tools / DB / DW	Business Objects, Crystal Reports, Tableau, Power BI, Alteryx, Data Integrator, Universe Designer, Xcelsius, Oracle, MS SQL, Netezza, Sybase, DB2, SQL, Kimball, Inmon, Data-Vault, Datawarehousing	
Python, Scala, JMP, SPSS, Visual Basic, C++, SQL, HTML, JIRA, ESB		
OS / Network / Protocol/Server	AWS Cloud, UNIX, LINUX, Windows, AD, LDAP, DNS, DHCP, RDP, SMTP, TCP/IP, FTP/HTTPS/Telnet/VPN/Clustering/load balancing	

EDUCATION, QUALIFICATIONS & TRAINING

Current:

• Master of Technology in Enterprise Business Analytics, NUS ISS (Part Time)

Completed:

2019: Managing Business Analytics Project, NUS ISS, Singapore

2019: Advanced Customer Analytics, NUS ISS, Singapore

2019: Customer Analytics, NUS ISS, Singapore

2019: Big Data Engineering for Analytics, NUS ISS, Singapore

2019: Data Storytelling, NUS ISS, Singapore

2019: Project Management Professional, Singapore (Examin Sep)

2019: Data Science Immersive, General Assembly Singapore

2006: SAP Business Objects, SAP Crystal Reports Certifications, MCSE Certification

2000: Master of Science in Software Engineering, Andrews University, US (GPA 3.6 out of 4)

1993: Bachelor in Electrical & Electronics Eng., University of Manchester, United Kingdom

1990: Diplomas in Electrical Engineering, Singapore Polytechnic

CAREER HISTORY

General Assembly & IMDA, Singapore

Data Science Immersive Graduate

Nov 2018 - April 2019

3-4 months Full Time Intensive Data Science & Machine Learning course

Learning Lab, Singapore

Data Analytics Manager + Architect

Aug 2018 - Oct 2018

Responsibilities:

- Data warehouse Project Manager as well as a Data Architect to setup a "Data warehouse team" for in-house Big Data Initiative.
- Interviewed candidates, contractor, system integrators, consultants and vendors for hiring as well as partnership engagement.
- Managed AWS Data Lake project with real time analytics with SI.
- Managed Data Dashboard Analytics & Visualization project using Tableau, Power BI Alteryx, Qlik Sense and SQL Server 2016

National Broadband Network (NBN Co), Australia

June 2015 - July 2018

Business Intelligence Project Manager

- Managed a project team of 11 members involving BI development for address search using "Elastic Search" with backend enterprise messaging bus KAFKA.
- Led a team of 4 for a BI platform to provide technical support, enhancements defects development and critical escalation support.
- Led in adopting SAFE Agile framework, i.e. PI planning, sprints planning, identify user stories, daily scrum meeting, story points allocation, product owner and stakeholder meeting, retro meeting, JIRA, Agile wall / Story Wall
- Acted as scrum master to the scrum team.
- Provided regular reports and status update to key stakeholders, management, and product owners.

Achievements:

• Successfully completed 7 projects of various sizes resulting in cost saving of around \$2 million AUD. Improved efficiency and better customer experience.

Australia Securities Exchange (ASX), Australia

Business Intelligence Manager

Oct 2012 - March 2015

- Led a project team of BI developers, business analysts, testers to define KPIs & reporting requirement; analysing business data, data mapping and gap analysis,
- Managed BI reports development for multiple projects involving BO reporting, KPI and analysis for activities, developed schedule and budget, risk and contingency plan.
- Planned projects by identified deliverables, created work breakdown structure, estimated resources, time, cost requirement, cost-benefit analysis.
- Assigned resources to testers to develop test strategies and plans.
- Analysed, designed, developed, tested and implemented BO solutions.
- Mentored interns and junior staff with SAP BI Enterprise knowledge.
- Led a team technical support engineers for DevOps of data-warehouse's applications & BO systems
- Managed BI administration tasks in various environments, i.e. UAT, SIT & production.
- Managed performance tuning for: reports, universes, SQL queries, etc.
- Supervised and completed system, functional and operational documentation.
- Monitored ongoing project activities, project variables against scheduled baseline plan

Achievements:

- Established best practice mandatory guidelines for developing universes, reports and scheduling, publication.
 - o E.g. standardised naming convention when migrating with export "biar" file.
 - Enforced mandatory check-out and check-into repository for universes, reports.
- Resolved performance issue by managing BO servers' workload of burst reports, multiple sub-reports, and concurrent schedules.
- Improved reports' generation time by dividing reports' workload with multiple publications; instead of just one single publication.

Fujitsu Consulting - Australia

Business Intelligence Principal Consultant

June 2008 - Sep 2012

Dept. of Immigration (1 year)

May 2011 – Jul 2012

- Acted as scrum master to communicate daily to key stakeholders and team members on deliverables' progress, releases, impediments, and milestone reviews.
- Conducted sprint review and sprint retrospective to review completed deliverable, reflected on past sprint, identified improvement actions, refinement of backlog.
- Involved in analysis, gathering, designing, developing, implementing, documenting and providing support for BO products.
- Implemented BO solution involving full development cycle:
 - E.g. Data mapping, designed universe, developed reports, created dashboards, installed servers & clients, setup AD/SSO authentication, configured users & groups, access level setup, testing, scheduling and publication.
- Upgraded and migrated older BO version to the latest.
- Resolved support issues for reports and ETL.
- Conducted BO training for users on Ad-hoc reporting & analytics capabilities.

Achievements / Projects:

- Managed project service delivery timelines and met clients' expectations.
- Troubleshooted a complex data issues via reconciliation back to the source system.
- Department of Immigration, Canberra
 Worked as a BO consultant for "Work permit & Visa Reporting" system. Led
 development of "linked" universes, Webi reports against DB2 DW.
 Created dashboards, Crystal and Xcelsius reports with interactive charts.
- Service First (NSW Government)
 Provided consultancy suggestion for Crystal reports development involved SAP
 Integration kit connecting to BW queries of FICO reports
- Runge Mining Developed Crystal reports with Integration kit connected to R3's tables for FICO reports. (i.e. Balance Sheet report)
- Visys Packaging Developed new reports which converted existing financial reports within SAP BW to Crystal reports.

PRIOR ROLES

Dialog IT Consulting - Australia

Senior Business Intelligence Consultant Aug 2007 – May 2008

SAP Australia

BI Technical Services Consultant, Business Objects Feb 2006 – July 2007

Actuate Reports - Singapore

BI - Senior Support Consultant Feb 2002 - Nov 2005

Standard Chartered Bank - Singapore

Senior Analyst Programmer Jan 2000 – Jan 2002

WEBSITES:

https://github.com/vyap2000

https://medium.com/@vyap2000

NATIONALITIES:

• SINGAPOREAN & AUSTRALIAN PR